欢迎回来, 在这个视频中, 我们将继续我们关于词汇的讲座
Welcome back, In this video, we're going to continue our lecture on lexical
通过一些过去编程语言的例子进行分析
analysis with some examples from past programming languages where interesting
词汇问题出现了, 我们已经讲了一些关于Fortran的内容
lexical problems arose. So we've already talked a little bit about Fortran and what
在Fortran中有趣的词汇规则是白色空间
are the interesting lexical rules in Fortran is the white space is
无关紧要的白色空间并不重要, 像VAR1这样的东西
insignificant so white space doesn't matter and something like VAR1 to which
可以是变量名VAR1和VA R1是一样的所以这两个程序
could be a variable name VAR1 is exactly the same as VA R1 so these two program
片段的意思是完全一样的东西用Fortran的思想就是你
fragments have to mean exactly the same thing sand the idea in Fortran is that you
可以使用你的程序你可以删掉它的所有空格, 这是不应该的
can take your program and you could delete all the blanks from it and that shouldn't
改变程序的意义, 让我们看一个例子
change what the program means at all. Let's take a look at an example of how
Fortran的白色空间规则影响词法分析, 这里有几个Fortran语言。
Fortran's white space rule affects lexical analysis. Here are a couple of Fortran
代码片段, 我应该说这个例子是从龙书中提取的
code fragments and I should say that this example is taken from the dragon book and
实际上, 后面的几个例子也来自于旧版本的
actually couple of the later examples were also taken from an older edition of the
龙书, 但不管怎样, 我们这里有, 这实际上是一个Fortran的头
dragon book. But anyway what we have here, this is actually the header of a Fortran
循环, 你知道它是一个循环因为它有一个关键字, 就像四个
loop. And you know it's a loop because it has the key word do, which is like four in
现代的C或C++所以我说循环关键字然后我们有了迭代变量I
modern C or C++ so I'd say loop key word And then we have out iteration variable I
我们有一个范围, 我将会改变, 在这个例子中, 我将从
and we have a range that I will vary between. So, in this case I will go from
1到25, 然后这个数字5, 这有点奇怪, 有点奇怪
one up to 25. And then this number five here, this is a little bit odd, something
你在现代语言中看不到, 在过去的Fortran语言中你会有你的
you don't see in modern languages. In the old days in Fortran you would have your do
在循环顶部的语句然后是循环的大小或者所有的语句
statement at the top of the loop and then the size of the loop or all the statements
在循环中包含了一个标签, 它们在做了之后就出现了
included in the loop Were named by a label, they came right after the do
语句, 所以, 循环会从, 标题, do语句延伸到
statement. So, the loop will extend from the, the header, the do statement down to
标签5, 所以无论什么语句都可以用5, 所有的语句
the label five. So whatever statement was able with five, all of the statements in
中间是循环的一部分, 所以循环会执行这些语句
between would be part of the loop. And so, the loop would execute those statements
然后我们回到标题, 然后继续执行, 直到它
then we'll go back around to the header and then we keep executing those until it
对于迭代变量的每一个值都这样做了, 在本例中, 是1
had done so for every one of the values of the iteration variable, in this case, one
到25, 这是另一个代码片段你们可以看到这个几乎是
to 25. Now, here's a nother code fragment and as you can see this one is almost
和上面的一样, 唯一的区别是, 我换一下
exactly the same as the one above. The only difference is, let me just switch
颜色, 在这里这个特殊的片段在那个位置有一个逗号
colors, is here that this particular fragment has a comma in that position and
这个片段有一个周期, 结果是这个差使所有的
this fragment has a period. And it turns out that this difference makes all the
不同的是这两个代码片段意味着完全不同的东西, 所以, 这个
difference that these two fragment of code mean completely different things. So, this
片段, 第一个, 实际上是一个循环, 就像我之前说的那样它有
fragment, the first one, is in fact a do loop as I said before so it has the
关键字do, 标签5, 变量I和范围1到25, 现在这个片段
keyword do, the label five, the variable I and the range one to 25. Now this fragment
在这里, 这实际上是一个变量名, 做5I, 到目前为止没有
down here, this is actually a variable name, do 5I, So far as writing without the
空格, 记住空格不重要, 这是5I, 这是an
blanks. Remember the blanks don't matter, This would be do 5I and this is an
赋值等于数字1.25, 好了, 你们可以看到这些符号,
assignment equals the number 1.25. Okay, And so you can see here these symbols, the
序列, 第一个符号序列的解释完全不同
sequence, the first sequence of symbols is interpreted completely differently
取决于是否有一个句号或者一个逗号, 所以我们就做一个
depending on whether there's a period or a comma further on. And so let's just be a
更准确的说, 我们怎么知道是什么呢？让我们把注意力集中在
little more precise about that. How do we know what do is? So let's just focus on
这里的关键字是这样的当我们在这一点的时候, 当我们的焦点在这里
the keyword here do and when we're at this point, when our focus is here right after
0, 记住, 这个要实现的方法是
the zero. And keep in mind that, that the way this is going to be implemented is by
从左到右的扫描所以我们要沿着这个方向走
a left to right scan so we're going to be walking in this direction over the, over
当我们的焦点到达时, 输入将会成功地观察每个字符
the input looking at each character successfully and when our focus reaches
这一点, 我们可以做一个决定, 这是a, 这是关键字, 因为我们
this point, we can make a decision. Is this a, is this a keyword 'cause we've
也看到了整个关键字, 问题是我们没有信息
seen the entire keyword too. And the problem is that we don't have information
来做这个决定, 我们不知道这是做还是不做
to make that decision. We don't know whether this is do or whether it's going
最终成为一个变量名的一部分, 比如5I, 唯一的方法是
to be eventually be part of a variable name like do 5I. And the only way to know
在这个位置的输入中看看是否有逗号或者
is to look ahead in the input to this position to see whether there's a comma or
这是一个需要向前看的词汇分析的例子。
a period there. So this is an example of lexical analysis that requires look ahead.
为了理解应得的角色, 我们要从左到右, 我们必须选择
In order to understand the role of due, as we're going left to right. We have to pick
在输入之前看到一些符号稍后会出现, 我们不可能
ahead of the input to see some symbols that come later on. And we can't possibly
消除歧义的作用直到那个poin t因为到这个点, 序列和
disambiguate role of do until that poin t because up to this point, the sequence and
符号是完全一样的所以唯一能区分它们的是
the symbols are exactly the same and so the only thing that distinguishes them is
这是一种更深入的东西, 你可以想象, 有很多
something that's much, much further on. And as you can imagine, having lots of
展望未来使词汇分析的实现变得更加复杂, 因此
look ahead complicates the implementation of lexical analysis and so one of the
在词汇系统的设计中, 目标是尽量减少未来的阅读量。
goals in the design of lexical systems is to minimize the amount of the look ahead
或者限制未来的阅读量, 所以你可能想知道为什么是Fortran
or bound the amount of look ahead that is required. So you might wonder why Fortran
关于白色空间有一个有趣的规则, 结果是在打孔机上
has this funny rule about white space. It turns out that on punch card machines it
很容易在事故中添加额外的空格因此他们将这条规则添加到
was easy to add extra blanks by accidents and as a result they added this rule to
这种语言, 穿孔卡片操作符不需要重做所有的工作
the language so the punch card operator wouldn't have to redo their work all the
幸运的是, 今天我们不再在打孔卡上输入我们的程序了。
time. Fortunately today we don't enter our programs anymore on punch cards. But this
例子可以帮助我们更好地理解我们在词汇中要做的事情
example does help us understand better what we're trying to do in lexical
分析, 正如我所说的, 目标是分割字符串, 我们试着买
analysis so as I said the goal is to partition the string. We're trying to buy
将字符串连接到语言的逻辑单元中, 这是由
the string up into the logically units of the language. And this is implemented by
从左向右看, 所以我们在做左向右扫描输入,
reading left to right. So we're doing a left to right scan over the input,
在一段时间内识别一个令牌。正因为如此, 展望未来可能是
recognizing one token at a time. And because of that, look ahead may be
需要决定一个令牌的结束和下一个令牌的开始, 再一次, 我
required to decide where one token ends and the next token begins. And again, I
想要强调的是, 向前看总是需要的但是我们想要最小化
want to stress that look ahead is always needed but we would like to minimize the
看前面的量, 事实上, 我们喜欢把它和这个常数联系起来,
amount of look ahead. And in fact, we like to bound it to some constant to this,
因为它将简化词汇分析器的实现
because it will simplify the implementation of lexical analyzer quite a
现在来说明一下我们一直都要担心的问题
bit. Now just to illustrate to look ahead is something that we always have to worry
让我们考虑一下这个例子我们之前已经看过了, 注意一下
about. Let's consider this example which we've looked at before and just notice
当我们从左向右看时, 让我们看一下这个关键字, 什么时候
that when we're reading left to right, let's look at this keyword else here, when
我们读了E, 我们要决定它是一个变量名还是某个符号, 但它本身
we read the E. We have to decide is that a variable name or some symbol but itself or
我们想要把它和跟随它们的符号一起考虑, 所以
do we want to consider it together with the symbols that follow them. And so
这里有一个展望, 在我们对E进行扫描之后, 我们必须决定它是坐着的
there's a look ahead issue here. After we scanned E, we have to decide does that sit
或者它是一个更大的词汇单位的一部分？而且, 你知道有一个
by itself or is it part of a larger lexical unit? And, you know there a re
在这个例子中, 单字符变量名, 如I, J和Z, 所以它不是
single character variable names in this example like I, J, and Z and so it's not
不合理的E也可以是另一个例子是这个双等号。
unreasonable that E could also be one and another example is this double-equals.
当我们读到一个等号时, 我们如何判断它是否等于一个等号
When we read a single equal sign, how do we decide whether that's a single equals
就像其他的作业一样或者它是一个双等号, 为了
like these other assignments or that it's really a double-equals. Well, in order to
这样做, 如果我们的焦点在这里, 我们必须向前看, 看到。
do that, if our focus point is right here, we have to look ahead and see. There's
另一个=上来这就是我们如何知道或如何知道的, 我们想要
another = coming up and that's how we know or how we will know. That we wanted to
把它合并成一个单独的符号, 而不是单独考虑这个等号。
combine it into a single symbol instead of considering this equals by itself. Another
例如, 很久以前的一种语言, 听不清是一种有趣的语言。
example from a, a language from long ago PL [inaudible] is a interesting language.
它是由IBM设计的它代表的是编程语言1, 好的, 它是
It was designed by IBM and it stands for Programming Language One. Alright, It was
它被设计成编程语言, 至少在IBM可以使用的情况下
designed to be the programming language. At least with an IBM that would be used by
每个人都应该包含所有程序员的所有特性
everybody and is supposed to encompass all the features that every programmer would
曾经需要, 因此, 它应该是非常非常普遍的并且很少有
ever need. And as such, it was supposed to be very, very general and have very few
限制, 所以, PL的一个特点是关键字不是
restrictions. And so, one of the features of PL [inaudible] is that Keywords are not
保留, 所以, 在PL, 你可以使用关键字作为关键字
reserved. So, in PL [inaudible] you can use a keyword both as a keyword and also
作为一个变量, 你可以使用关键字和其他角色而不是关键字
as a variable. So you can use keywords and other roles other than keywords and that
意思是你可以写有趣的, 有趣的句子或者有趣的句子
means you can write interesting, interesting sentences or interesting
像这样的程序, 让我把它大声读出来因为它听起来很像
programs like this. And let me just read this out loud because it sounds
很有趣, 如果是这样的话, 那么, 其他的, 其他的, 还有正确的组织
interesting, if else then, then = else, else = then. And the correct organization
当然, 这是一个关键字, 这是一个关键字, 这是一个关键字。
here of course is that this is a keyword, this is a keyword and this is a keyword.
另一件事, 换个颜色, 都是变量, 这些都是变量
And the other things, switch colors here, are all variables. These are all variable
名字, 你可以想象这混合了词法分析有些困难
names. And as you can imagine this mix a lexical analysis somewhat difficult
因为当我们从左向右进行扫描时就像我们从这里穿过的时候
because when we're just scanning left to right like when we're coming through here
当我们说到这一点的时候, 你知道我们如何决定这些东西
when we say we're at to this point, you know how do we decide whether these things
将会是变量名或关键字而不需要看到其他的情况
are going to be variable names or keywords without seeing what's going on in the rest
在这个表达中, 在PL的词法分析是相当具有挑战性的
of the expression so lexical analysis in PL [inaudible] was quite challenging. So
这是另一个来自PL的例子, 我们有一个程序
here's another example from PL [inaudible]. Here we have a program
片段, 我们有单词声明, 然后是一个开放的paren和一个亲密的paren
fragment, we have the word declare and then an open paren and a close paren
包含了一堆参数所以我们要指出这里的平衡
encompassing a bunch of arguments so we'll point out the balance parens here and then
只是在括号内的n个东西的列表, 结果是
just a list of n things inside the parens. And it turns out that the pending on the
更大的上下文, 整个表达式都在这里, 这可以是a
larger context in which this whole expressions sits, this could be either a
关键字, 也可以是数组引用这意味着什么时候, 这意味着声明
keyword. Or it could be in array reference that mean when, yeah, that mean declare
这里可以是一个关键字也可以是一个数组的名字这可以是
here could either be a keyword or it could be a name of an array and this could be
这是数组的结尾, 当它发生的时候, 没有办法看
the end [inaudible] to the array. And as it happens, there is no way looking at
这是我们可以决定的, 这个片段是有效的, 是一个有效的声明
just this much that we can decide. This fragment is valid, is a valid declaration
它也是一个有效的数组引用, 所以, 它取决于接下来会发生什么。
and it's also a valid array reference. So, it would depend on what came next. It
例如, 是否有一个等号, 在这里是否有一个等号
might depend on for example whether there was an equal sign here in which cases
将被解释为一个赋值, 并且声明将是一个数组的名称。
would be interpreted as an assignment and, and declare would be the name of an array.
这个例子的有趣之处在于, 因为
And, the interesting thing about this example is that because the number of
这里的参数是无界的, 对于任何n, 都可以有n个。
arguments in here is unbounded. There could be n of them for any n. This
需要无限的向前看, 好的, 为了在你扫描的过程中正确地实现这个
requires unbounded look ahead. Okay, So to implement this properly as you're scanning
从左到右决定是否再次声明是一个关键字或重新引用, 我们
left to right to decide whether declare again is a keyword or re-reference, we
需要扫描整个参数列表, 看看接下来会发生什么。
would have to scan beyond this entire argument list to see what came next.
Fortren和PL是在20世纪50年代和60年代分别设计的
Fortren and PL [inaudible] were designed in the 1950s and 1960s respectively and
这些经历教会了我们很多关于在词汇设计中不应该做什么
those experiences taught us a lot about what not to do in the lexical design of
编程语言, 所以今天的情况好多了但是问题还没有
programming languages. So things are a lot better today but the problems have not
完全消失了, 我将用一个C++的例子来说明这一点
gone away completely and I'll use an example from C++ that illustrate this. So
这里有一个C++模板语法的例子你们可能很熟悉, 也可能是
here's an example of C++ template syntax which you may be familiar with or you may
在Java中也见过类似的语法, 而C++有另一个名为Stream的操作符
have seen the similar syntax in Java. And C++ has another operator called Stream
输入, 所以这里的操作符从输入流中读取并将结果存储在a中
Input. So this operator here reads from an input stream and stores the results in a
变量, 问题是, 这里有一个嵌套模板的冲突,
variable. And the problem is, here that there's a conflict with nested templates,
举个例子, 如果我有一个像这样的模板, 好的。
So for example, if I have a template o peration that looks like this. Okay.
注意这里发生了什么, 我的目的是要有一个嵌套的应用程序
Notice what happens here. So my intention here is to have a nested application of
模板, 但最后我得到了两个伟大的符号
templates but I wind up with two great than signs together at the end and this
看起来就像流操作符一样问题是, 词汇应该是什么
looks just like the stream operator and the question is what should the lexical
分析者做了吗？应该把它解释为模板的两个括号或者应该
analyzer do? Should it interpret this as two close brackets for template or should
它将其解释为两个大于作为一个流操作符的符号。
it interpret it as a two greater than signs stuck together as a stream operator.
事实证明, 在很长一段时间里, 我认为大多数C++编译器都有
And it turns out that for a very long time, I think most C++ compilers have now
修正了这个, 在这种情况下, C++编译器会把它看成一条流
fixed this. The C++ compiler in this situation would regard this as a stream
操作符, 你会得到一个语法, 你认为解决方案是什么
operator and you would get a syntax there. And what do you think the solution was, it
结果是, 你能做的唯一的解决方法就是对这个问题进行分析
turns out that the only fix that you could really do to make this lexically analyzed
正确的方法是插入一个空白, 这样你就必须写这个, 你会
the correct way was to insert a blank so you would have to write this and you would
一定要记得把空白放进去这样两个大于符号的
have to remember to put the blank in there so that the two greater than signs were
不是在一起, 你知道这是一种丑陋的东西我们必须把它放在空白的地方
not together. And you know that's kind of ugly that we have to put in white space to
修正了程序的词汇分析, 总结了词汇的目标
fix the lexical analysis of the program. So to summarize the goal of lexical
分析是将输入流划分为lexemes, 好的, 我们已经下降了
analysis is to partition the input streams into lexemes, okay. So we have drop down
在字符串中划分线来决定lexemes在哪里, 我们想要
dividing lines in the string to decide where the lexemes lie and we want to
识别每个词素的标记, 因为, 正是因为我们在做一个
identify the token of each lexeme, And because, exactly because we're doing a
从左到右扫描, 有时我们必须向前看, 有时我们需要偷看
left to right scan, sometimes we have to have look ahead. Sometimes we have to peek
在输入字符串中, 找出我们正在看的当前字符串,
ahead in the input string to figure out what the current string we're looking at,
我们现在看到的子串是什么, 它在语言中扮演什么角色？
what the current substring we're looking at, what role it plays in the language?